Hey class, this is
another Rapid Farm concept
review question, and we have
a 29-year-old male treated
for Hodgkin's lymphoma,
and he reported to his
physician with complaints
of urinary frequency,
pain, and blood in the urine.
So based on this
question, one could
assume that he might
be having a UTI,
but as we read further,
the urine culture
was done, and it was
negative for the
presence of bacteria.
A cystoscopy
revealed a thickened
bladder wall with
diffuse erythema.
Which of these is the most
likely causative agent?
So looking at the choices,
we see these are all anti
-neoplastics. So we have
to say to ourselves that
this effect is most likely
due to an adverse effect.
of one of these.
So if I had to put
these words together,
this would likely be a case of
something called
hemorrhagic cystitis.
And with that, we
know that a specific
alkylating agent does
induce this effect.
And the ones I'm
thinking about are mainly
a phosphomide or
cyclophosphomide. So I will
say that, yeah, this
is the best answer.
But since we want to
consider and learn from these
questions, it's important
that we look at the
at the other answer choices.
So cisplatin is considered
to be an alkylating agent.
And remember, an alkylating
agent does just that.
It makes a bulky alkyl
group that binds to N7 of
guanine to cause strand
breaks. So obviously when that
happens, you can't get DNA
replication. but cisplatin
does so with a platinum
atom in the group and
cisplatin is widely used
for solid tumors lung cancer
carboplatin is used mainly
for cases of ovarian
cancer and oxaloplatin is
a third generation, and
that's when it's used as
part of colon cancer therapy.
And the thing to know about
the platinums, anything
that has a metallic group
attached to it is not going
to be so easy for the
kidney to excrete. So the
platinums have a high
risk of ototoxicity, so to
hearing and the vestibular
apparatus, and also neurotoxicity.
So somewhat you can
say that the adverse
effects of the platinums
mimic that of aminoglycoside
antibiotics. So if you
were to have a patient that
was treated with an
antineoplastic like this, and you
needed to treat, say, a
gram-negative aerobic rod,
I would probably shy
away against using an
aminoglycoside. I would
try to find another
antibiotic because you
can induce nephrotoxicity.
Doxorubicin is ruby, okay,
and it's colored
red. That's how
we, in pharmacy,
would recognize it.
And that kind of
made us know from
the get-go that when
that word is said,
we think of dilated
cardiomyopathy.
This is an intercalating
agent. So, very simply, it
gets in between the strands
of the DNA to cause breaks.
And the other thing,
it causes ROSs.
and what will happen
is that the ROSs
will affect the
contractile proteins
that are responsible for the
smooth muscle contraction
in the heart and if
that does get affected,
you're going to have the
patient experience somewhat
of what you might see
in a patient that has
congestive heart failure. So,
cardiotoxicity, doxorubicin.
the vincas and the taxanes
are mitotic spindle
poisons where the vincas
will inhibit polymerization
of the microtubules and
the taxanes will inhibit
the depolymerization okay
they are also used in
various cancers but
vinblastine is one of the most
myelosuppressive drugs
among the chemotherapies
and first aid credit to them
puts it very nicely blasts
the bone marrow and then
vincristine is the one that
will induce something called
pins and needles so the
patient will feel like
maybe that then cessation of
their hands or their foot
falling asleep so that's an
important adverse effect of
vincristine. And then, of
course, you know, always
understand that these drugs,
especially if you're
talking about cisplatin, you
know, you need to have
some type of anti-emetic
on board. And that will
be something that I will
discuss next semester
when I cover antiemetics.
So with the idea of what
creates acrolein is the fact
that cyclophosphamide and
n-phosphamide is a pro
-drug. So once activated, the
cytotoxic metabolite goes
to N7 of guanine and does
the job of causing the DNA
breaks. And then the acrolein
will go to the bladder
and now you have this
metabolite that is going to
irritate the bladder. So the
way we manage is number one
mostly to prevent with
adequate hydration and the
other thing is to give a
sulfonated compound known as
mesna because mesna will go
on and bind the acryoline.
So thank you for
your attention.
I hope you found this
helpful, and if there are
any questions, please
feel free to contact me.
Have a great day, everyone.